Guide to the African-Americans in the Spanish Civil War: Research Files ALBA.143
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
African-Americans in the Spanish Civil War: Research Files
1930-1994
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade
Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives
ALBA.143
1 Linear Feet (1 box)
The material in this collection was accumulated during research for and production of the book, African Americans in the Spanish Civil War: "This Ain't Ethiopia, But It'll Do" (G. K. Hall, 1992), and for an ALBA-supported research project on this topic. The lack of available information on the approximately 90 African Americans who volunteered and served with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War spurred the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives support organization (ALBA) to pursue this project. ALBA Executive Director Danny Duncan Collum was the book's Editor and Victor A. Berch, who was the archivist for the ALBA collection at Brandeis University, was Chief Researcher. The collection includes files on individual volunteers, research notes, drafts of Robin D. G. Kelley's introduction to the book, permissions forms, meeting minutes, work logs, and publicity items. Also included is one reel of microfilm containing relevant U.S. State Department documents.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Provenance
This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Historical/Biographical Note
The material in this collection was accumulated during research for and production of the book, African Americans in the Spanish Civil War: "This Ain't Ethiopia, But It'll Do" (G. K. Hall, 1992), and for an ALBA-supported research project on this topic. The lack of available information on the approximately 90 African Americans who volunteered and served in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War spurred the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA) support organization to pursue this project. ALBA Executive Director Danny Duncan Collum was the book's Editor and Victor A. Berch, who was the archivist for the ALBA collection at Brandeis University, was Chief Researcher. The project was supervised by a working committee appointed by the ALBA Board of Governors.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically. Material is organized in 3 series:
Missing Title
Series I: Individual Research Files, 1933-1990.
Series II: Book Production/Research Files, 1989-1994.
Series III: Microfilm--National Archives Publication M973, "Purport Lists for the Department of State Decimal File, 1910-1944."
Separated Materials
Photographs were separated from the following individuals' files: Walter Dicks, Theodore Gibbs, and Otto Reeves. Photos were temporarily moved to ALBA PHOTOS 164 (Box 6) and will eventually be integrated into ALBA PHOTOS 15.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains files on individuals, correspondence, minutes, work logs, production and publicity files, and microfilm of relevant documents of the U.S. State Department.
Series I: Individual Research Files, 1933-1990. This series contains research material relating to individuals profiled in the book African Americans in the Spanish Civil War: "This Ain't Ethiopia, But It'll Do" (1992) and some other material on volunteers. Files include copies of U.S. State Department and other official records, research notes and citations, correspondence, and interview transcripts. Also included are a group of files of official correspondence relating to individuals -- most of them not African-Americans -- who stowed away on the SS Normandie. [Note: Files with the following labels, found in the collection, were empty: Chesterton, Tomas Collado, Gerald Goldwyn, William Moore, Tom Trent.]
Series II: Book Production/Research Notes, 1989-1994, contains material relating to the production and publication of the book. Files include correspondence, research notes, introduction drafts, permissions forms, meeting minutes, work logs, and publicity items.
Series III: Microfilm--National Archives Publication M973, "Purport Lists for the Department of State Decimal File, 1910-1944." This series consists of one reel of 35mm microfilm produced by the National Archives and Records Administration and containing U.S. State Department Records pertaining to the Spanish Civil War. Included are a chronology of war events and international involvement, information on U.S. enlistments (filed alphabetically by surname), lists of Spanish army equipment and supplies, and information on naval activities. Files are titled "Decimal Files," 852.01/16-852.42765/2. Film is NARA Microfilm Publication M973, Roll 400.
Research notes.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x African Americans.; Collum, Danny Duncan; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Berch, Victor A.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives
- Series I: Individual Research Files, 1933-1990. (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Frank Edward, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Archer, Amos, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baker, William, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Battle, Thaddeus Arrington, Jun-Oct 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Beebe, Vernold, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brown, Tom, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Callion, Walter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Carter, Council Gibson, Jul 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chisholm, Albert, Oct 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cleveland, Roland, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Coad, Mack, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cobbs, Walter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Collins, Leroy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cox, James, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Deserters (U.S.), State Dept. Documents re: Jamieson, W. Edward; Maier, Henry Rudolf; Rudnisky, William, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dicks, Walter, Apr 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Donawa, Arnold Bennett, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dukes, Larry Stratford, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Durem, Ray (Ramen, a.k.a. Ramon), 1969-1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ford, James, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Frankson, Kanute Oliver, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Gamis y Cabrera, Domingo, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Garland, Walter Benjamin, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Gavin, Eugene Victor and Robert Owen, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - George, Henry, Jul 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gibbs, Theodore, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Graham, Meredith Sydnor, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Gutierrez, Centurio, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Harvey, George, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Haywood, Harry, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Herndon, Milton, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Hughes, Langston, Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Hunter, John Dudley, Jul-Aug 1937 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hunter, Oscar Henry, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Jackson, Burt Edward, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Johnson, Edward, Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Kee, Salaria (a.k.a. Salaria Kea), 1937-1979 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Kilpatrick, Admiral, Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Law, Oliver, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Lewis, Abraham, Undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Lisberg, Norman, Apr 1939 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Love, Vaughn, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - McDaniels, Eluard Luchell, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Mitchell, Andrew, Undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Morgan, Crawford, Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Page, Thomas, Undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Parker, Charles Augustus, Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Peck, James Lincoln Holt, 1941-1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Pickens, William, Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Pringle, Claude, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Prowell, Alpheus Danforth, Undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Reeves, Otto, Undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Rhetta, Virgil, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Roach, Douglas, Undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Robeson, Paul, 1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Rochester, Sterling, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Rodriguez, Julius, Undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Roosevelt, Patrick, Undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Rosario, Conrado Figueros, Undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Seacord, Douglas, Undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Beebe, Wernold, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Byczek, Walter, Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Garrett, James, Aug 1938 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Groups Lists, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Hartsell, Marshall, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Holland, Willard, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Kaplan, Bernard, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Lukomnik, Israel, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: McManus, Jerome, Aug-Oct 1938 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Parker, David, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: Ulanoff, Henry, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Stowaways on the S.S. Normandie: White, John, Aug-Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Swanson, West, Undated (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Taylor, Joseph, Undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Thornton, Ralph, Undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Verdier[e], Herbert, Jun-Jul 1939 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Waters, George Walter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Watson, Alonzo, Undated (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Weiderman [Widerman], Jefferson, Undated (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - White, William Edward, Oct-Nov 1937 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Wickman, Morris Henry, Undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Williams, Fred, May 1938-Aug 1939 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Williams, Paul E., 1938-1988 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Willis, Sam, Undated (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Yates, James, Undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Youngblood, Charles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
- Series II: Book Production/Research Notes, 1989-1994.
  - Berch, Victor: Log of Hours Worked, Oct 1989-Jan 1994 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Collum, Danny Duncan: Correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Kelley, Robin D. G.: Introduction, Draft (first), Aug 1990 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Kelley, Robin D. G.: Introduction, Draft with notations by George Watt and Bill Susman, Sep 1990 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Permissions: Forms and Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Project Announcement, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Project Committee: Meetings, Nov 1989-Apr 1990 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Publicity and Reviews, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Research Notes: African-American Volunteers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Research Notes: Home Front, Undated (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Research Notes: Not Used, Undated (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Research Notes: Used, Undated (Box 1, Folder 99)
- Series III: Microfilm--National Archives Publication M973, "Purport Lists for the Department of State Decimal File, 1910-1944."
  - Roll 400, Decimal Files 852.01/16 - 852.42765/2 (35mm Microfilm), 1930-1939 (Box 1)